Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting Yale University Women
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Kirk, Elizabeth, 2007 November 1; Accession 2012-A-045
  Elizabeth Kirk's interview includes an extensive exploration of her Quaker upbringing and education, recollections of her powerful and academically accomplished mother, and an account of how those influences profoundly affected her experience of the academy at Yale and beyond. She describes her first encounter with Yale culture in the late 1950s and the social, psychological and practical challenges that women graduate students and junior faculty faced. This is placed within the context of the Yale tenure system and the effect it had in determining relationships between junior and senior faculty in the English Department. She pays tribute to E. Talbot Donaldson's qualities as a teacher and mentor of women at Yale, especially in his role as Director of Graduate Studies. Her experience of being one of the first women fellows at Calhoun College is described, including how it differed from that of her male peers, among whom was her husband. She talks about other women in the Yale English Department, especially her fellow medievalists, Marie Borroff and Alice "Sunny" Miskimin. Throughout the interview she highlights specific instances and experiences, at Yale and beyond, which led her to conclude that many of the difficulties women encountered in the academy were not personal but institutional. Her experience of combining marriage with academic life is recalled, together with the challenge of carving out independent intellectual space.
  Kirk describes how she obtained her position at Brown University and details the cultural differences she perceived between Yale and Brown at that time. She talks at length about her passion for teaching and mentoring at both Yale and Brown, in particular her role as Director of Brown's Honors Program and as one of the authors who redrafted the Brown Medieval Curriculum. She reflects on how her experiences as a Yale graduate student shaped and informed her emerging feminism, and how her growing feminist perspective influenced her work as Director of Graduate Studies at Brown. An account is given of what she saw as gendered differences in the way that graduate students and junior faculty were treated, especially when it came to hiring and promotions. She talks in general terms about the Lamphere vs. Brown University case, with which she was involved, and how it confirmed her view of the importance of due process and transparency to obviate what she regards as systemic inequalities in the academic profession. From that time forward, policy issues increasingly became the major focus of her professional life at Brown. She reflects on the challenge of attempting to maintain a balance between administration and teaching, and the personal costs of this conflict in both psychological and practical terms. As Brown's first female chair of the English department, she considers how far her management style and practice was influenced by her gender, and the pressures which led her to take early retirement.
  - Audiorecording, 5; ; 3 hours and 45 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Mahar, Margaret, 2008 December 7; Accession 2012-A-046
  The interview is closed until January 1, 2040.
  Margaret (Maggie) Anne Mahar was born in 1949 into an Irish-American, Roman Catholic, working class family. She was raised in Syracuse, New York. Higher education was not a family priority, but she was one of the few in her high school who aspired to a college education. Her parents reluctantly allowed her to apply to Middlebury College, Vermont., which admitted her. However, when Mahar discovered that Middlebury could not provide a scholarship, she turned to a local Syracuse resident who donated the full cost of her college education. She loved Middlebury but when she heard, in her sophomore year, that Yale University was about to admit women, she got a transfer. Mahar graduated in 1971, one of the first cohort of co-educated women at Yale, and remained for graduate work in English, earning a Ph.D. in 1975. In 1974 she was hired as an instructor in the English Department, and from 1975-1982 worked there as an assistant professor, during which time she married and had two children.
  When she was denied promotion to associate professor, Maggie Mahar left the academic profession and became a journalist, thus fulfilling her lifelong ambition to be a writer. Since then she has been a financial journalist, contributing to Barron's, Money, The New York Times and other newspapers and magazines. She is the author of Bull! A History of the Boom, 1982-1999: What Drove the Breakneck Market – and What Every Investor Needs to Know about Financial Cycles (Harper Business, 2003) and Money-Driven Medicine: The Real Reason Health Care Costs So Much (Collins, 2006). Money-Driven Medicine was the basis of a documentary produced by filmmaker Alex Gibney, released in 2009. Maggie Mahar produces Healthbeatblog.org for The Century Foundation, a daily blog which investigates and debates healthcare and medical issues.
  Maggie Mahar talks at length about the ways in which class, race and gender intersected in her growing up, and how class, in particular, was articulated in her college years at Middlebury and Yale; she felt different from the other Yale women co-eds. She also discusses class and gender relations among the undergraduates, and to what extent gender was an issue between faculty and students. She recalls the events surrounding May Day, 1970, an encounter with President Kingman Brewster, and teaching freshman English as a Carnegie Fellow in her senior year. Her attitudes to feminism and feminist issues are described; she recalls that the Yale curriculum addressed the issue of homosexuality in literature some time before feminist theory was introduced. She talks about her reasons for choosing Yale for graduate work, the challenges she faced as a woman graduate student, her relations with other women graduate students, and her attitude to sexism and sexual harassment. She discusses the influence of Yale scholars like Harold Bloom, Geoffrey Hartmann and J. Hillis Miller when she was a graduate student, and how their approach to literature influenced her own teaching and scholarship. An account is given of her appointment to the English Faculty at Yale; the differences in the way male and female undergraduates responded to a woman teacher; her attitude to teaching women writers; her experience of academic administration, and departmental attitudes to pregnancy and motherhood. A description of how the Yale tenure system worked at that time, and her own expectations, is then given, along with a lengthy review of the circumstances surrounding her denial of promotion to associate professor. In particular she reflects on her relationship with the then acting chair of the department, Ronald Paulson. A generational gap opened up on the faculty with the influx of younger scholars, men as well as women, from the late 60s onwards; Mahar discusses how this played out in relations between women faculty.
  Finally, Mahar talks about how she made the transition from academia to journalism, and her subsequent career as a financial journalist. This involves a comparison of academic culture with that of the financial world.
  - Audiorecording, 2; ; 2 hours and 15 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Mintz, Jacqueline Wei, 2008 December 9; Accession 2012-A-047
  Permission to access must be obtained from interviewee until January 1, 2020.
  Jacqueline Wei Mintz was born in 1935, in Shanghai, China. Her father was in international banking and decided to move the family to the United States in 1941, shortly before the U.S. entered World War II. The family moved around the New York area for a time before settling in Bronxville. Mintz attended the local public school before entering Abbot Academy (now Phillips Academy). From there she went to Radcliffe College where she majored in linguistics, with minors in Persian and Arabic.
  In 1958, she began a Ph.D. in linguistics at Yale. Whilst still a graduate student she met Sidney Mintz, an anthropologist on the Yale faculty. They married in 1964. Mintz did not complete her doctorate but in the ensuing years, between extensive study and research periods at M.I.T., then in Iran and Paris, she held a variety of positions in the Yale administration. First, she worked for the recently-established Carnegie funded 5-year B.A. program. She was Dean of Saybrook College in the academic year 1971-1972, during which time she also served on Yale's Undergraduate Admissions Committee. In 1972, she was appointed Associate Provost with responsibility for developing Yale's affirmative action program and for preparing Yale's first Affirmative Action Plan which was submitted to U.S. Department of Heath, Education and Welfare in April 1973. She held this position until she resigned in 1976.
  After she left Yale, Mintz moved to Baltimore where her husband was now teaching, and took a law degree at the University of Pennsylvania. Then she worked in Washington, D.C., first for the National Labor Relations Board, and then the American Association of University Professors. She then specialized in consumer protection law in Baltimore, before moving to the Maryland Attorney General's Office where she worked in educational affairs until her retirement.
  Jacqueline Mintz begins the interview by briefly outlining her family and educational background and touching on her ethnic identity. A lengthy account is then given of her first impressions of Yale and the city of New Haven, and the experience of living in Helen Hadley Hall, the women graduate residence which opened its doors the year she arrived at Yale. She describes what she perceived as the prevalent attitudes towards women at Yale, within the faculty and amongst her graduate peers and the undergraduates. She recalls being at Yale in the sixties as a young faculty wife, and her and her husband's relations with young faculty and students, particularly their involvement with, and commitment to, the new generation of undergraduates who were admitted to Yale as a result of the changes in admissions policy instituted under Inslee "Inky" Clark, Dean of Undergraduate Admissions, 1965-1970. Encounters with minority student leaders like Armstead Robinson and Glenn de Chabert are detailed at length, and how the Sixties counter culture and political issues, such as civil rights and the anti-Vietnam war protests, began to change the Yale campus and relations within it. In this context she assesses her early attitudes to feminism, the advantages and disadvantages of being a faculty wife, and how the so-called nepotism rules impinged on her life.
  Mintz briefly describes her involvement with the innovative 5-year B.A. program, the reasons why her husband declined an offer – a joint decision by the couple - to become the Master of Pierson College. The circumstances in which she was offered the deanship of Saybrook College are discussed, along with the many challenges the job, especially those relating to gender and race. She assesses to what extent her gender was an issue for the undergraduates and the college fellows.
  Most of the rest of her interview is taken up with her years as Associate Provost. As Yale's first affirmative action officer she had responsibility for the development and implementation of Yale's affirmative action program. She discusses attitudes and perceptions regarding affirmative action which then prevailed in the Yale administration and faculty, especially the intense debate surrounding the role of goals, quotas and timetables in implementing government policy, which took place against a background of stringent budgetary restraints. A description is provided of how she approached the challenges of gathering data for, and then drafting, Yale's first Affirmative Action Plan. She discusses relations with the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare at both an institutional and personal level, singling out many specific issues, including: the removal of the anti-nepotism rule from the Faculty Handbook, the 'pipeline' issue in respect of women and minority hiring on faculty, and the first attempts to secure regular ladder appointments for longstanding female adjunct faculty. Mintz stresses the fact that her job entailed the development of an affirmative action program for all university employees, not just faculty, and how this responsibility brought her into contact with clerical, managerial and professional staff, and with bargaining units across the entire university. During her tenure, she set up the first faculty search and recruitment procedures for each department and school at Yale, and completed an M & P Salary and Job Classification Study (which affected over 1500 employees, many of them women). This revealed significant wage discrepancies and other forms of discrimination. In conclusion she discusses the reasons why she resigned in 1976, and briefly describes her professional life after she left Yale.
  In the course of the interview, Mintz recalls personal encounters with, and impressions of, many senior Yale figures of the period, including President Kingman Brewster, Provosts Hannah Holborn Gray and Richard Cooper, and Dean Howard Taft. She talks about her friendship with Marnesba "Bobbi" Hill, the first African-American women to serve in the senior Yale administration (Assistant Dean of Yale College, 1973-1974 and Associate Dean, 1974-1980). She also recalls networks of women she found useful outside Yale, and her role as a founding member, along with Bobbi Hill, of a group called New England Minority Women Administrators.
  - Audiorecording, 3; ; 3 hours and 30 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Morse, Charlotte, 2008 May 26; Accession 2012-A-048
  Charlotte Cook Morse was born in Washington, D.C. on October 26, 1942, and was brought up in rural Loudon County, Virginia. After graduating with a B.A. degree from Brown University in 1964 she pursued graduate studies at Stanford University where she received an M.A. in 1968 and a PH.D. in 1970. In 1968 Morse came to Yale as an instructor in the Department of English, and from 1969-1976 served as an assistant professor. During the period 1975-1976 she also was a program officer for the National Endowment for the Humanities in Washington, D.C. In 1976 she was appointed an associate professor at Virginia Commonwealth University, and in 1994 promoted to full professor. She remained at VCU until her retirement in 2011.
  Morse won the second national Betty Crocker Homemaker of Tomorrow Scholarship in 1960, held a Pembroke College Southern Regional Scholarship while at Brown University, received a Leverhulme Fellowship in 1967-1968, held a Morse Fellowship from Yale 1971-1972, and was twice the recipient of an NEH Fellowship, 1982 and 1991.
  Morse is the author of a number of books and articles on medieval literature, including Pattern of Judgment in the Queste and Cleanness (University of Missouri Press, 1978). In addition, she co-edited several volumes of essays in honor of the medieval scholars J.A. Burrow, V.A. Kolve and Judson Boyce Allen. She serves on the editorial boards of The Chaucer Review and The Journal of The Early Book Society.
  Charlotte Morse talks about her upbringing and education, paying particular attention to her family history and expectations, in the context of the rural culture in which she was raised in Loudon County, Virginia. She recalls how she came to choose Brown University for her undergraduate studies, and how she secured funding for her college education. She outlines the gender imbalances of the National Merit Scholarships in the late 1950s, as well as her experience of winning the Betty Crocker Homemaker of Tomorrow award, which largely funded her undergraduate years at Brown. She describes the academic and social culture she encountered at Brown, including faculty attitudes to women faculty and students. She acknowledges the intellectual inspiration and practical mentoring of the historian Harcourt Brown and the English literature scholar Barbara Lewalski (one of the few women on the Brown faculty at that time), and recalls friendships with her female student peers. She reflects on the academic and professional aspirations of her peer group, and the restrictions relating to gender which they believed were imposed on women's careers.
  An account is given of why she chose Stanford University for graduate work in English, and what it was like there during the era of civil rights and opposition to the Vietnam war. She discusses the challenge of combining marriage with the academic life, a subject which is a running theme throughout the interview. Morse recounts her experience of the academic job market of the late 1960s, the kinds of discrimination facing women, and the circumstances of her appointment at Yale. She speculates as to why Yale's English Department appointed so many women to junior faculty positions at that time. A lengthy description is provided of the culture then prevailing in the Yale English Department and the wider Yale community, particularly life in Morse College and the ways in which Yale changed socially and culturally during the late 60s. Morse originally iterated the challenges of being an academic woman in a written submission to the Greene Committee on the Status of Professional Women at Yale (1971). These issues are revisited in her interview, especially sexual harassment and the complexities of combining work and marriage. She also addresses the difficulties of the Yale tenure system and the lack of formal mentoring for both male and female junior faculty, and how far gender complicated these matters. Many of the senior English faculty, including Maynard Mack, Thomas Greene, Martin Price, W.K. Wimsatt, Frederick Robinson and Bart Giamatti, are recalled. Morse pays special tribute to Marie Borroff, who was then the only tenured woman in the English Department.
  Her appointment to Yale coincided with the arrival of the first women undergraduates; she reminisces about them and some of the challenges they faced. Morse also recalls the events surrounding May Day, 1970, and her encounter with some of the early feminist groups at Yale around this time. She summarizes the general indifference to, or ignorance of, women's issues in the English Department until the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare equal rights regulations were passed in 1972. In particular she remembers a conversation with Bart Giamatti in which they discussed how these changes in the federal law would affect Yale.
  Morse recounts how the oil crisis of 1974 and the subsequent recession affected university recruitment, and what this meant in her own life as she went onto a retrenched job market in search of a tenure-track position, whilst dealing with the crisis of her failing marriage.
  Finally she talks about the legacy of Yale, how it influenced her subsequent teaching and scholarship, and pays tribute to the medievalists who nurtured her scholarship and intellectual life, in particular the British scholars Eric Stanley and John Burrow (both of whom held visiting appointments at Yale).
  - Audiorecording, 4; ; 5 hours and 33 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Phillips, Rolly, 2008 March 28; Accession 2012-A-049
  Rolly Phillips was born March 31, 1943, in Brooklyn, New York. Brought up in Pocatello, Idaho, she is the eldest of six children. Her mother was the first woman to graduate from the University of Idaho Law School and was a practicing lawyer all her life. Phillips gained her B.A. from Bryn Mawr College in 1965. She then spent two years as a Fulbright Scholar at Newnham College, Cambridge, England. She earned a Ph.D. in classics from Harvard in 1970. After teaching summer school at the University of Massachusetts, Boston, she was hired by Yale as an Instructor in Classics in the fall of 1970. At that time there was only one other woman in the department, a lecturer, Anne Parry, wife of then Chair, Adam Milman Parry. From 1971-1977, Rolly Phillips was an Assistant Professor in Classics. Knowing that she was unlikely to get tenure, she left Yale and taught for almost three years at Barnard College, New York. She then decided not to continue a career in higher education and obtained a position teaching classics at Fieldston School, New York, where she still teaches.
  Rolly Phillips discusses her upbringing and education, paying tribute in particular to her mother as a role model of the successful professional woman. She recalls her undergraduate years at Bryn Mawr, especially the social challenges she experienced. She recalls teachers like Richard Lattimore, the classicist and poet. She describes life as a female graduate student at Harvard and Cambridge Universities and the cultural differences she encountered. In particular she recalls some of the difficulties faced by female scholars at Harvard. Dr. Phillips talks about how she was hired by Yale, and the encouragement she received from Eric Havelock, Sterling Professor of Classics. She touches on the issue of affirmative action, relationships between junior and senior faculty, and between women faculty, and talks at length about the pleasures of teaching Yale undergraduates, both men and women. She discusses tenure at Yale and why she believed she was unlikely to achieve it. She briefly recalls her time at Barnard College, and concludes her interview by discussing her reasons for choosing a career of high school teaching. She describes how her teaching experience at Yale influenced her teaching younger students at Fieldston School.
  - Audiorecording, 1; ; 1 hour and 56 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Polan, Mary Lake, 2007 November 28; Accession 2012-A-050
  Mary Lake Polan was born July 17, 1943, in Las Vegas, New Mexico and grew up in Huntington, West Virginia. The eldest of four children, her father was an ophthalmologist, her mother a housewife. After early schooling in Huntington, her high school years were spent at the Emma Willard School in Troy, New York. She graduated from Connecticut College in 1965, cum laude and Phi Beta Kappa, having also completed a Smith College Junior Year Abroad in Paris 1963-1964. Polan enrolled in Yale University in 1965 as a graduate student in the Department of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry (M.B.B.), earning her Ph.D. in 1970. From 1970 to 1972 she was an Instructor and Lecturer in M.B.B. as well as a postdoctoral fellow in the laboratory of Dr Joseph Gall, in the Yale Department of Biology, the second year of which was funded by a National Institutes of Health Postdoctoral Fellowship.
  Professor Polan entered Yale University School of Medicine in 1972, gaining her M.D. in 1975. She spent several months of her medical training at Oxford Medical School, Oxford University, England, as a Clinical Clerk in Obstetrics and Gynecology and in Pediatrics at the Radcliffe Infirmary, Oxford. From 1975-1978 she was a Resident in the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Yale University School of Medicine, the first woman ever to complete a residency in that department. In early 1978 she spent several months as an Instructor in Obstetrics and Gynecology at Pahlavi University, Shiraz, Iran, followed by a similar appointment at Yale. After her residency she held two fellowships in the Yale Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, the first in Oncology and the second in Endocrinology and Infertility, during which time Polan had the first of her three children.